Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is ח, Chet, בבא
מציעא Bava Metzia 8, and we pick up with 1 2 3
4 5 6 7 lines from the top, אמר רמי בר חמא.
Amar Rami Bar Chama. The eighth line starts with the word חמא.
chama. Okay, and our learning should be in memory of my nephew
מעוז מוראל Moz Morel and תפילה tfillah for the safety and security
of our troops. Okay, we pick up with אמר רמי בר חמא.
Amar Rami Bar Chama. We had a whole discussion about how exactly
do the splitting and a שטר, shtar, and now we're getting back
to the משנה mishna about יחלוקו. yachloku. אמר רמי בר חמא, Amar
Rami Bar Chama, זאת אומרת, zot omeret, from this משנה mishna we
learn המגביה מציאה לחבירו קנה חבירו hamagbia metzia lachaveiro kana chaveiro that
if somebody picks up a lost object for somebody else, then the
other person takes possession of it.
And at some level what's the חידוש? chidush? Like there's a general
principle of זכין לאדם שלא בפניו, zachin leadam shelo befanav, you can
do something on behalf of somebody that's to their benefit even not
in their presence. But that normally is when let's say somebody is
giving a gift and says to you here take this gift and
take it in for possession of ראובן, Reuven, you can do that
no question. But here, when you are picking up a lost object,
by the fact that you're picking it up for ראובן, Reuven, means
that somebody else can't, you're disadvantaging somebody else. So that might be
why you would because now nobody else is it's not free for
somebody else to pick up and to keep. So you might think
that you can do it for yourself but maybe you're not empowered
to do it for somebody else at the expense of other people.
So he says from our משנה mishna we see that the principle
is המגביה מציאה לחבירו קנה חבירו, hamagbia metzia lachaveiro kana chaveiro, it
does work. Now how do you know that? אי סלקא דעתך Isalka
deitach לא קנה חבירו, lo kana chaveiro, if the if you could
not do it for the other person, תעשה זו כמונחת אגבי קרקע
וזו כמונחת אגבי קרקע ולא יקנה לא זה ולא זה. teiasei zu
kemunachat agabei karka vezu kemunachat agabei karka velo yikneh lo zeh velo
zeh.
In a case where they both picked it up, רמי בר חמא
Rami Bar Chama is inferring from our משנה, mishna, and we'll see
why in a little bit, that our משנה mishna implies that if
they both picked it up simultaneously they both take possession of it,
right? And you remember one case of the משנה mishna is אני
מצאתיה, ani matzatiha, I found it, it was a lost object free
for taking. So רמי בר חמא Rami Bar Chama says, if that
were the case they both picked it up simultaneously, how does it
work? I picked up my end of it, the other guy picked
up his end. I did not pick the whole thing off the
ground. He did not pick the whole thing off the ground. So
neither of us did a קנין. kinyan. And therefore, nobody should own
it and some third party can come and take it. Okay, he
says like so that's כמונחת אגבי קרקע, kemunachat agabei karka, it should
be like the other half for each of us it should be
the other half is on the ground and neither of us should
be קונה. koneh. Why does it work? Because when I picked it
up for me, if I also picked it up for him, and
when he's picking it up for himself he's also picking it up
for me, then for both of us did we do a full
picking up. I did my picking up of my half combined with
his picking up of his half for my sake, and he did
his picking up of his half plus my picking up of his
half for his sake. I did his picking up of his half
for my sake and he did his picking up of his half
plus my picking up of his half for his sake. Now obviously
why would I want to do that? Right, because don't I want
the whole object? Why am I doing it to benefit him? But
because I want some of the object and the only way it's
going to work is if we assume that I want to pick
it up for him and I will pick it up for him
if he'll pick it up for me, you know that's therefore we
assume that that is taking place because otherwise neither of us would
take possession. So רמי בר חמא Rami Bar Chama says, since when
they both pick it up they both own half, that shows that
each one is seen as operating on behalf of themselves and behalf
of the other person to consider it that each person did a
full picking up off the ground. And that teaches you המגביה מציאה
לחבירו קנה חבירו. hamagbia metzia lachaveiro kana chaveiro. Okay, so let's take
a look and again we don't know exactly where he sees in
the משנה mishna that that scenario means they're both קונה, koneh, we'll
get to that. But that's what he's inferring from that scenario that
if two people pick it up they both get it.
אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא, Rava, לעולם אימא לך המגביה מציאה
לחבירו לא קנה חבירו. leolam eima lach hamagbia metzia lachaveiro lo kana
chaveiro. No, I could tell you that normally I see an object
that's free for the taking, I pick it up for ראובן, Reuven,
ראובן Reuven doesn't own it.
והכא היינו טעמא מיגו דזכי לנפשיה זכי נמי לחבריה. Vecha hainu taama
migo deizachi lenafshei zachinei nami lechavrei.
Because you're taking possession for yourself you can also take possession for
the other person. Not because you're able to take possession for yourself,
that's a classic case of מגביה מציאה. magbia metzia. I see this,
I could have taken it for me instead I pick it up
for ראובן. Reuven. But because you're that maybe we wouldn't say, you
know, you're disadvantaging other people like I said. But if you're actively
taking possession of yourself, so you're taking it away from the ability
of other people to be קונה, koneh, you are taking it for
yourself, in that act of taking for yourself you could also have
somebody else and take it on behalf of someone else. And in
the case of two people pick it up they both own half.
people picking it up, each one is picking it up on behalf
of themselves, and because it's the only way the קנין kinyan will
work, on behalf of the other person. So it works better when
you're already doing it for yourself and you can't prove that it
would work when you're solely doing it for the other person. Okay,
now
תדע, Teida, now I will prove to you that this makes a
difference when you're being קונה koneh for yourself or solely for the
other person.
תדע שאילו אמר לשלוחו צא וגנוב לי. Teida she'ilu amar lishlucho tzei
ugnov li. You say to your שליח, shaliach, go steal for me
this object from ראובן Reuven and he steals it. Okay, וגנב פטור,
veganav patur, you're exempt. Now, you're exempt obviously אין שליח לדבר עבירה,
ein shaliach lidvar aveirah, but it also means, you know, we've learned
that there are certain types of קניינים kinyanim for גניבה וגזלה gneivah
ugezeilah and he's taking it to, you know, in his act of
trying to steal it that gives him maybe certain קניינים kinyanim which
comes with certain liability. None of that affords to you, okay, because
what he's doing is an illegal act. So even if he wants
to do it for you, you know, that does not become like
you were קונה koneh that גניבה. gneivah. Okay, ושותפין שגנבו, veshutfin sheganvu,
however, if two people sneak into somebody's, you know, apartment and they
carry out the sofa and they take it together, okay, ושותפין שגנבו
חייבים. veshutfin sheganvu chayavim. They're חייב. chayav. Now, how does that work,
right? Again, each one only picked up half of the sofa. So
מאי טעמא, mai taama, what's the reason? לאו משום דאמרינן מיגו דזכי
לנפשיה זכי נמי לחבריה. lav mishum de'amrinan migo de'zachie l'nafsheih zachie nami
l'chavreih. So even though, you know, ראובן, Reuven, if he tried to
steal for me, I wouldn't be קונה, koneh, but if, when he
is stealing for himself, he's also stealing for me, you know, then
I am קונה. koneh. All right, so therefore, and especially if we
imagine that we're doing it together, so we're both sort of stealing
for ourselves and for the other person. Okay, but even though clearly,
so that's exactly the same case, we're both picking up a sofa
and schlepping it out just like this case. Okay, but he says,
but nevertheless, when you try to do it by yourself, it doesn't
work. So if that's true by גניבה, gneivah, you know, well clearly
that's illegal, but maybe it's also true by מציאה metziah because other
people are being disadvantaged.
Okay, so it says like this,
all right. ושותפין שגנבו חייבים מאי טעמא לאו משום דאמרינן מיגו דזכי
לנפשיה זכי נמי לחבריה. veshutfin sheganvu chayavim mai taama lav mishum de'amrinan
migo de'zachie l'nafsheih zachie nami l'chavreih. שמע מינה. shma mina. אמר רבא.
Amar Rava. So that's a good point, that those cases are different.
So you can't prove it from two people picking up a מציאה.
metziah. All right, that might not be able to generalize from that
from one person picking it up for somebody else. אמר רבא השתא
דאמרת אמרינן מיגו. Amar Rava hashta de'amrat amrinan migo. Now that you're
saying that there is this principle, since I'm doing it for myself,
even though something I wouldn't be able to straight do for someone
else, I can piggyback them on what I'm doing for myself. If
that's true, השתא דאמרת אמרינן מיגו חרש ופיקח שהגביהו מציאה. hashta de'amrat
amrinan migo cheresh u'pikeiach she'higbihu metziah.
Let's say you have a חרש, cheresh, somebody who's deaf and mute,
and a פיקח, pikeiach, somebody who is, you know, neither those, normal,
you know, somebody without those disabilities. So, and they both pick up
a מציאה. metziah. Now, here's the thing.
A חרש cheresh cannot be
קונה koneh anything מן התורה. min haTorah. He's not considered, הלכה Halacha
doesn't consider בר דעת. bar da'at. הלכה Halacha evolved about that, about
its status about a חרש, cheresh, but in the, within the גמרא,
Gemara, it does not consider a חרש cheresh to be a בר
דעת bar da'at and he doesn't have agency and he doesn't have
like legal standing and he can't be קונה koneh something. However, the
Rabbis were instituted because of דרכי שלום, darchei shalom, that, you know,
ways of peace, that if he finds something, and he, you know,
that he's considered to own it. But not in terms of it's
a real קנין, kinyan, but we treat it as his because of
דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. Okay, so now a פיקח pikeiach and a
חרש cheresh picks up up an object at the same time. So
the חרש, cheresh, they only allowed him to take possession of the
things for himself, this idea of דרכי שלום, darchei shalom, not for
somebody else. So they're both lifting it up, neither one did a
full lifting it up. The, so again we're going to sort of
surmise that in order for it to work they want each one
wants to do it for the other person. חרש cheresh wants to
do it for the פיקח, pikeiach, פיקח pikeiach wants to do it
for the חרש. cheresh. So let's see what we've got. Okay, מתוך
שקנה חרש קנה פיקח. mitoch she'kanah cheresh kanah pikeiach. Because the חרש,
cheresh, because the חרש cheresh is קונה koneh for himself, he could
also be קונה koneh for the פיקח. pikeiach. All right? מתוך שקנה
חרש קנה פיקח. mitoch she'kanah cheresh kanah pikeiach.
So now the גמרא Gemara says one minute. בשלמא חרש קנה דקא
מגבה ליה בן דעת. bishlama cheresh kanah de'ka magbei lei ben da'at.
I get why the חרש cheresh is קונה. koneh. The פיקח pikeiach
picks it up for himself and for the חרש. cheresh. So somebody
who's normally considered a בן דעת, ben da'at, you know, somebody who's
like a, you know, an actor within the legal system, he can
be קונה koneh it for the חרש. cheresh. Just as you can
be קונה koneh for ראובן, Reuven, you can be קונה koneh for
a חרש. cheresh. Okay, אלא פיקח במאי קני. ella pikeiach bemai kani.
How is the פיקח pikeiach קונה? koneh? He needs the חרש cheresh
to be קונה koneh for him for that half to be considered
picked up for him. But the חרש cheresh is never has the
power to do a real קנין. kinyan. He's just treat, something he
takes for himself we let him we treat it as if it's
his because of דרכי שלום, darchei shalom, but he can't do a
real קנין. kinyan. So the, so from the פיקח's pikeiach perspective, the
פיקח pikeiach didn't pick the whole thing
up. So the
גמרא Gemara
says אלא אימא ela eima fine,
you're right, say it this way: חרש קונה פיקח לא קונה. cheresh
koneh pikeach lo koneh. Okay? The חרש cheresh is קונה, koneh, חרש
cheresh picked up his half, and the second half that the פיקח
pikeach picked up, he was picking it up on account of himself
and the חרש. cheresh. So from the חרש's cheresh perspective, both halves
were picked up. From the פיקח's pikeach perspective, פיקח pikeach only picked
up his half, but the חרש cheresh did not work, so the
פיקח pikeach gets nothing. But for the חרש, cheresh, he gets both
halves. Okay? So, so אלא אימא חרש קונה פיקח לא קונה. ela
eima cheresh koneh pikeach lo koneh. ומה מיגו? u'mai migu?
What's the because of? Like that's just the straight application, you know?
So no, מיגו דשני חרשים בעלמא קנו. migu deshnei charashim be'alma kanu.
The same way if two חרשים charashim were to pick it up,
we should assume they're קונה koneh because if one חרש cheresh we
let him be קונה koneh because of this דרכי שלום, darchei shalom,
two חרשים charashim who pick it up simultaneously, we let them be
קונה. koneh. So therefore האי נמי
קני. hai nami kanei. So this case with a חרש cheresh and
a פיקח, pikeach, we let the
חרש's, cheresh
פיקח's pikeach picking up, it shouldn't be any worse than the חרש.
cheresh. The פיקח's pikeach picking up works for the חרש. cheresh. But
the חרש's cheresh picking up does not work for the פיקח. pikeach.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, היי מאי? hai mai? What
are you talking about? אם תמצא לומר מגביה מציאה לחבירו קנה חבירו.
im timtzi lomar magbi’ah metzia le-chavero kanah chavero. If you were to
tell me that normally when you pick something up for חבירו chavero
he owns it, הני מילי hani mili meaning even if you go
back to the forget מיגו דזכי לנפשיה. migu dezachi l'nafshei. Even if
you go back to the basic teaching of רמי בר חמא Rami
bar Chama that you can straight pick it up and take possession
for somebody else, הני מילי היכא דקא מגבי אדעתא דחבריה. hani mili
heicha deka magbi ada’ata de-chaverei.
That's only if you're doing it for the sake of the other
person. Right? So if I pick it up for ראובן, Reuven, ראובן
Reuven is קונה. koneh. האי אדעתא דידיה קא מגבי לה. hai ada’ata
didey ka-magbelah.
Okay, like if you talk about what the פיקח pikeach is doing,
the פיקח pikeach is not this altruistic person. He's picking it up
fundamentally for himself. But what do we say? We'll also see him
as picking it up for the חרש cheresh because then we'll see
the חרש cheresh as picking it up for him. So that's the
arrangement we have to do in order that each one is considered
to pick it up fully. But fundamentally you're in it for yourself.
Okay. So if the פיקח pikeach is in it for himself, then
if it's not going to work for him, because the חרש's cheresh
picking up does not work for him, then why would he want
to be picking it up for the חרש? cheresh? Alright? אי לא
קני לאחריני אקני? ee lo kanei leachrini aknei?
If the פיקח pikeach isn't קונה koneh for himself because you're telling
me that what the חרש cheresh does doesn't work for me because
the חרש cheresh is only because of דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. So
if what the חרש cheresh is going to do isn't going to
work for me, I'm not going to be Mr. Altruism and pick
my half up for him as well.
So אי לא קני לאחריני אקני? ee lo kanei leachrini aknei? Do
I want the פיקח pikeach to be קונה, koneh, do I want
to be מקנה makneh it, do I want to pick it up
for the חרש? cheresh? No. Alright? So whether you say מיגו דזכי
לנפשיה migu dezachi l'nafshei or מגביה מציאה לחבירו, magbi’ah metzia le-chavero, in
this case if you the פיקח, pikeach, what you the פיקח pikeach
is doing can work for the חרש, cheresh, what the חרש cheresh
is doing cannot work for you. So if what the חרש cheresh
is doing cannot work for me and I'm going to wind up
with nothing, then I'm also not going to do it on his
account either. Okay, אלא אימא ela eima fine, so go back to
reverse what we said, say the following: מתוך שלא קנה פיקח mitoch
she-lo kanah pikeach because I as the פיקח pikeach am not going
to get it because the חרש's cheresh picking up won't work for
me, so לא קנה חרש. lo kanah cheresh. Then I'm also not
picking it up for the sake of the חרש cheresh and at
this stage like neither of us will own it. Okay. וכי תימא
מאי שנא משני חרשים בעלמא? v'chi teima mai shena mishei charashim de'alma?
How is when a פיקח pikeach and a חרש cheresh picks it
up different than when two חרשים charashim pick it up, which we
assume that they both are קונה koneh half? התם תקינו להו רבנן
דלא
אתי
לאינצויי. hatam takinu lehu rabanan delo atei l'inyatuyei. Okay, there basically the
rabbis established it so that they should not come to fight. So
but הכא מימר אמר hacha meimar amar
but here he'll say, the פיקח pikeach would say פיקח לא קני
אני אקני? pikeach lo kanei ani aknei? If the פיקח pikeach isn't
going to get, you expect me to get?
Okay, so
meaning so when two חרשים charashim pick it up, right, because we've
established this whole idea that a חרש cheresh can pick up a
מציאה metzia because of דרכי שלום darchei shalom and so on, we
don't want to go ahead and say oh if they both of
them pick it up we're going to drop our דרכי שלום darchei
shalom and we're going to let somebody else come and grab it
from them, right? That would be completely unfair. And then the חרשים
charashim are going to say this is totally unfair. If two פיקחים
pikchim were to pick it up you would let them keep it,
so now it's the two of us the two חרשים charashim you're
going to let somebody grab it from us? So there's this injustice,
it'll lead to fighting, we have to extend our תקנה takkana to
that case as well. And also they're on the same plane. If
a חרש cheresh can pick it up for himself for דרכי שלום,
darchei shalom, he can pick it up for his friend for דרכי
שלום. darchei shalom. But by this case of a חרש cheresh and
פיקח pikeach where the חרש cheresh cannot do it for the פיקח,
pikeach, now and we're going to let a third party come and
grab it, we say neither of them are קונה, koneh, the חרש
cheresh is not going to say that it's unjust. Because the פיקח
Pikeach is getting the same treatment. So you know, so we have
to let two חרשין Charashin be like two פיקחין Pikchin or else
it'll be unjust. But if it's a חרש Cheresh and a פיקח,
Pikeach, and we don't let the פיקח Pikeach be קונה, Koneh, we
also won't let the חרש Cheresh be קונה. Koneh. Okay? I mean
logically it shouldn't because of the mechanism and nobody is going to
cry that it's unjust because it's equally true for the פיקח Pikeach
and the חרש. Cheresh. All right, very good. Okay, now, אמר ליה
רב אחא בריה דרב אדא לרב אשי. Amar lei Rav Acha brei
de-Rav Ada le-Rav Ashi. So Rav Acha the son of Rav Ada
said to Rav Ashi: דיקא דרמי בר חמא מהיכא? Diyka de-Rami bar
Chama me-heicha? Where's Rami bar Chama getting this idea from our משנה
Mishna that if two of them pick it up at the same
time it works?
אי נימא מרישא, Ee neima me-reisha, if it's from the first case,
שניים אוחזין בטלית, Shnayim ochazin be-talit, two people are holding on, התם
האי קאמר כולה שלי ואנא אגבהתי כולה? Hatam hai ka-mar kula sheli
ve-ana agbahti kula? Who told you that they're claiming they picked it
up at the same time? Each one is saying it's all mine
and I picked it all up. האי כולה שלי ואנא אגבהתי כולה.
Hai kula sheli ve-ana agbahti kula. Excuse me, כולה שלי ואנא אגבהתי
כולה. kula sheli ve-ana agbahti kula. And the other one says it's
all mine and I picked it all up. So how do you
know that, what does that tell you about them picking it up
at the same time? אלא מהכא, Ella me-hacha, from here. אלא מהא
דתני זה אומר כולה שלי וזה אומר כולה שלי. Ella me-ha de-tani
zeh omer kula sheli ve-zeh omer kula sheli. The second case, not
just אני מצאתיה ani metzatia but the second case of כולה שלי.
kula sheli. So הא תו למה
לי?
ha tu lamma
li? Why do I need them that second case, not just אני
מצאתיה ani metzatia but כולה שלי? kula sheli? אלא משנייה תשמע מינה
המגביה מציאה לחבירו קנה חבירו. Ella mi-shniya tishma mina hamagbiya metzia le-chavero
kana chavero.
To tell you that, you know, now exactly logically how it's telling
you it's not clear, but since that's seen as like a redundant
case and not just saying אני מצאתיה ani metzatia but they're saying
כולה שלי, kula sheli, it's to tell you that even in a
scenario where they both picked it up at the same time then
they would equally own it. Now exactly again clear how we connect
the dots, but that's what we'll say is meant by the double
language. So the Gemara says: No, והא אוקימנא רישא במציאה וסיפא במקח
וממכר. ve-ha okimna reisha bi-metzia ve-seifa be-mekach u-mimkar.
We said that the two cases are to cover a case of
both a מציאה Metzia and a case of purchase, and there's nothing
extra there that's trying to get at some other idea of two
of them picking it up at the same time. אלא מסיפא, Ella
mi-seifa, fine, from the next case of the משנה, Mishna, the bottom
of the משנה. Mishna. זה אומר כולה שלי וזה אומר חצי שלי.
Zeh omer kula sheli ve-zeh omer chatzi sheli. One guy says all
and one guy says half. הא תו למה לי? Ha tu lamma
li? Why do I need that? אלא משנייה תשמע מינה המגביה מציאה
לחבירו קנה חבירו. Ella mi-shniya tishma mina hamagbiya metzia le-chavero kana chavero.
Okay,
that's to tell you that even if they picked it up at
the same time because otherwise it's obvious. Now it's not just in
this case, I think, that it's extra, so we'll say because it's
an extra case it's coming to teach us this new הלכה. halacha.
It's also the guy who's saying it's half mine, what's he saying?
Presumably he's saying that we both picked it up together. Now, not
necessarily, he could say, you know, I picked it all up but
I had in mind, you know, to only be קונה Koneh half
of it or something like that, all right, but presumably he's saying
that we picked it up together and that would teach you the
principle that if they both pick it up together they both own
it. So the Gemara says:
Okay, וממאי, u-mima'i, how do you know that's the case? דבמציאה, De-vi-metzia,
how do you know it's talking about a case of a found
object and that that, you know, and the claim of half means
we picked it up together? דילמא במקח וממכר. Dilma be-mekach u-mimkar. Maybe
it was the scenario of purchasing it and the owner intended to
sell half to me and half to him, and it's not a
case of, you know, we both picked it up at the same
time. It wouldn't matter what order it was, it's dependent on what
we paid for and what the owner's intent was. וכי תימא אי
במקח וממכר מאי למימרא? Ve-chi teima ee be-mekach u-mimkar mai le-meimra? So
then why do you need that case? Isn't that case an obvious
extension of the first case? No, איצטריך, itzrich, you need to tell
me a case of whole and half. דסלקא דעתך אמינא האי דקאמר
חצי שלי ליהוי כמשיב אבידה וליפטר. De-salka da-tach amina hai de-ka-mar chatzi
sheli le-havei ke-meshiv aveida u-lifter.
If I'm saying half is mine, I could have said it's all
mine and then I would have been entitled to half. Now I'm
going to say half is mine and as we know the משנה
Mishna teaches I'm only entitled to a quarter. So why don't we
say because I have could have made a bigger claim and I
could have got half by claiming it's all mine and now I'm
only getting a quarter by claiming it's half mine, then you should
believe me about my claim that it's half and you shouldn't force
me to make a שבועה. Shvuah. All right? So the Gemara says:
קא משמע לן דארומי קא ערים. ka mashma lan de-arumey ka-arem.
No, maybe you're just doing it all, maybe this is all a,
you know, deceiving. סבר אי אמינא כולה שלי מישתבענא, Savar ee amina
kula sheli bi-nishtavu'ei, I'll have to make a שבועה Shvuah and I
don't want to. אימא הכי, Eima hachi, I'll say it's half mine,
דהוה כמשיב אבידה, de-havei ke-meshiv aveida, it's like I'm giving up something
I don't have to give, וליפטר, ve-lifter, and I'll be exempt from
a שבועה. Shvuah.
So that's what the משנה Mishna is teaching. The משנה Mishna is
teaching whole and half not to teach you the half scenario, it's
not to teach you that if they pick it up at the
same time they equally own it, it's to teach you that even
when a guy claims half and he's willingly giving up his claim
to the other half, that does not get him out of a
שבועה Shvuah because he might be doing it specifically as a way
to get out of the שבועה. Shvuah. Okay.
אלא
מהא, Ella me-ha,
from this case. היו שניים רוכבין על גבי בהמה. Hayu shnayim rochvin
al gabei behema. If they were two of them were riding on
an animal. הא תו למה לי? Ha tu lamma li? Why do
you need that? I mean how is that telling you anything different?
and the case of the טלית. tallis. אלא מי משניה תהא שמע
מינה המגביה מציאה לחבירו קנה חבירו. ella mi mishneya teh shma mina
hamagbiya metzia lechavero kana chavero. So it's a totally extra case and
therefore it's telling you this principle of two people picking it up
again. How you get from one to the other is not clear,
but from the extra case we're going to tell you that it's
coming to hint to the idea that even if they both found
it at the same time and picked it up at the same
time, they both own it. So גמרא gemara says ודילמא הא קמשמע
לן דרוכב נמי קני, vedilma ha kamashma lan derochev nami kani, maybe
it's teaching you that riding also is a קנין, kinyan, even, you
know, maybe I might think that riding it as we'll see we're
going to discuss this in a minute in the גמרא, gemara, the
question about whether riding is a קנין, kinyan, and it's not the
classic קנין kinyan of משיכה meshicha of drawing the animal towards you.
Now if you're sitting on it and you're making it move, that
is משיכה, meshicha, but if you're just sitting on it without making
it move, so maybe there's a good reason to think that that
would not be considered a קנין kinyan and it's telling you it
is. So that might be telling you nothing about the idea of
two people picking it up at the same time. So אלא מסיפא,
ella maseifa, from the very end of that case, בזמן שהן מודין
או שיש להם עדים חולקין בלא שבועה, bizman shehen modin o sheyesh
lahem edim cholkin belo shvuah,
if they agree to what happened, that they both found it, you
know, or there are witnesses that say that they both own it,
then you divide it without a שבועה. shvuah. So במאי, bemai, what's
the case? אי במקח וממכר צריכא למימר? ei bemekach umimkar tzricha lemeimar?
If they're both agreeing that they both purchased half of it or
there are witnesses, of course, if they agree or if there are
witnesses, then it's obvious. אלא לאו במציאה? ella lav bemetzia?
It must be that it's telling you that there are witnesses or
they agree that they both own half because they both picked it
up at the same time. Oh, so that's now a חידוש, chiddush,
right? So then שמע מינה המגביה מציאה לחבירו קנה חבירו. shma mina
hamagbiya metzia lechavero kana chavero. So that teaches you this idea, if
they both picked it up at the same time they own it,
which teaches you the principle for רמי בר חמא Rami Bar Chama
that המגביה מציאה לחבירו קנה חבירו, hamagbiya metzia lechavero kana chavero, I
can pick up a מציאה metzia for ראובן. Reuven. So that actually
is a very nice read of the משנה. mishna. Why does the
משנה mishna have to tell me that if they both agree or
if there are witnesses, you divide it without a שבועה? shvuah? I
mean, of course, there are witnesses, what else would I think you'd
do? Ah, but what's the scenario where they both agree? There could
be a scenario where they both agree or I might think they
don't divide it. Maybe if they picked it up at the same
time, they're both agreeing to that, they're both saying they own half,
but maybe you don't divide it because maybe one guy's picking up
didn't work for the other. And that's teaching you, no, it does
work for the other when they both pick it up at the
same time. ורבא אמר לך, verava amar lach, רבא Rava would say,
look, I agree that that is the case the משנה mishna is
teaching, but I don't agree with your principle that you can סתם
stam pick up a מציאה metzia for ראובן. Reuven. He would say
to you מיגו דזכי לנפשיה זכי נמי לחבריה. migo dezachi lenafshei zachi
nami lechavrei. That works because since I'm being זוכה zocheh for myself
and I'm doing it, I can also do it on your behalf
and vice versa, and you're doing it for yourself and you're doing
it on my behalf, but that does not prove that I can
solely pick it up on your account. Okay, so that was the
question about המגביה מציאה לחבירו hamagbiya metzia lechavero and the idea of
picking it up at the same time. Let's now go on to
the case of both of them riding the animal. היו שנים רוכבין,
hayu shnayim rochvin, they were both riding it. אמר רב יוסף, amar
Rav Yosef, אמר לי רב יהודה, amar li Rav Yehuda, רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda said to me, שמעה מינה דבי מר שמואל, shmah mina
devei mar Shmuel,
I heard from שמואל, Shmuel, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was a תלמיד
talmid of שמואל, Shmuel, I heard from שמואל Shmuel תרתי, tarti, two
rulings. רכוב ומנהיג, rachuv umanhig,
riding or being ridden, not well being ridden, being on the animal
and leading the animal. חד קני וחד לא קני, chad kani vechad
lo kani, one of them works as a קנין kinyan and one
does not. Now it says רכוב rachuv and not רוכב rochev because
רוכב rochev
is
like if I'm riding an animal, that means that the animal is
moving and I'm making it move, and then that's just מנהיג. manhig.
Then that's a classic case of making the animal move, which is
a משיכה meshicha which works, okay? But this is a case of
I'm seated on the animal
and the question is, is that a קנין? kinyan? So you have
a guy that's just seated, which is רכוב, rachuv, and then you
have the case of מנהיג, manhig, somebody leading the animal. Now leading
is a classic case of משיכה meshicha which should work. But I
heard that שמואל Shmuel said that these two cases, being seated on
an animal and leading an animal, חד קני וחד לא קני, chad
kani vechad lo kani, one is קונה koneh and one is not.
ולא ידנה הי מינייהו, velo ydana hai minayhu, and I don't know
which is which. Now that seems a little bizarre because we know
מנהיג manhig works because of משיכה, meshicha, so let's see what the
גמרא gemara says. היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case? אילימא רכוב
לחודא ומנהיג לחודא, eileima rachuv lechuda umanhig lechuda, if it means a
guy just sitting on an animal and a guy just leading an
animal and we want to know one of those is, you know,
which one of those works as a קנין kinyan if you're buying
something or if you found a מציאה? metzia? So מנהיג
לחודא מי איכא מאן דאמר לא קני? manhig lechuda mi ika man
damar lo kani? Who would ever say that somebody leading an animal
is not קונה? koneh? That's classic משיכה, meshicha, of course that works.
So that can't be the scenario שמואל Shmuel was talking about. אלא
אי איכא למימר דלא קני, ella ei ika lemeimar delo kani, if
there's a scenario where maybe מנהיג manhig does not work, what would
be the scenario? Oh, excuse me, if there's anything that doesn't work,
רכוב הוא דאיכא למימר, rachuv hu deika lemeimar, then it would obviously
be רכוב. rachuv. So if you know that שמואל Shmuel said one
works and one doesn't and you're not sure which is which, you
cannot be talking about the case of each one coming independently, because
if each one came independently, you would have absolutely no... No question
that מנהיג Manhig works, it's classic משיכה, Meshicha, and רכוב Rachuv doesn't
work. Why should רכוב Rachuv work? It's not משיכה, Meshicha, you didn't
make the animal move. So because you don't know which is which,
you cannot be talking about the scenario of coming separately. אלא, Ela,
here must be the scenario we're talking about. רכוב במקום מנהיג איבעיא
ליה. Rachuv bimkom manhig ibaya lei. The question that שמואל Shmuel was
asking is if you have a guy that is רכוב Rachuv and
מנהיג Manhig at the same time, which one of them, you know,
beats out the other? Presuming that each one works independently—מנהיג Manhig we've
already established—let's also assume that רכוב Rachuv is a type of a
קנין, Kinyan, although we haven't heard of that before. Okay. What happens
when they come together? Is there one that is a stronger קנין
Kinyan and beats the other out? Now, we normally haven't heard about
a stronger קנין. Kinyan. You know, would we say, I don't know,
if two of us found a מציאה Metziah and one did a
משיכה Meshicha and the other did a הגבהה, Hagbahah, which is the
stronger קנין Kinyan that wins out? Okay, presumably not. But here,
you know, maybe the גמרא Gemara is considering the possibility that in
the, that it's, it's not just some objective scale one is stronger
than the other, but that maybe when they're coming together, one is
really showing real ownership. Okay. I mean, if you think about it,
if a guy is sitting on an animal and the other person
is leading it, you assume that the guy sitting on the animal
is the one that owns it. So it seems that the question
is not just so much which is stronger, because we normally don't
talk about competing קניינים, Kinyanim, you know, again, a משיכה Meshicha and
הגבהה Hagbahah coming at the same time which one wins out, but
maybe, you know, does one of them dominate in the presence of
the other and make the other not have the same meaning of
taking possession? Let's see how the גמרא Gemara frames it. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. אלא רכוב במקום מנהיג איבעיא ליה.
Ela Rachuv bimkom manhig ibaya lei. That was the question. מאי? Mai?
What's the story? רכוב עדיף דתפיס בה? Rachuv adif de-tafis bei?
Is רכוב Rachuv more, better because he's holding onto it? Now you
could say it means holding onto it with his legs, but we're
going to see that the, you know, the גמרא Gemara is going
to talk more about like holding onto it with its reins. Okay.
או דלמא מנהיג עדיף דאזל מחמתיה? O dilma manhig adif de-azal machmatei?
Is the guy who's leading it better that it's going on his
account? And so which one is seen as really demonstrating when they're
both there at the same time, you know, which one is demonstrating
real control and real ownership? That's the question.
Okay. And we don't know when they come at the same time
if, you know, שמואל Shmuel assumed that one of them wins out
and I don't remember which one he said wins out. Okay. I
don't remember what שמואל Shmuel taught about that. אמר רב יוסף, Amar
Rav Yosef, אמר ליה רב יהודה. Amar lei Rav Yehuda. Said, so
after רב יהודה Rav Yehuda taught, said he didn't remember what שמואל
Shmuel said, he's saying but רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said to me,
נחזי אנן. Nachzei anan. Let's try to figure it out ourselves. I
don't remember which one שמואל Shmuel said. Let's see if we can
figure it out ourselves. דתנן, De-tenan, we taught in a משנה Mishna
about
כלאים, Kilayim, about you're not supposed to plow with an ox and
a donkey at the same time, and we understand that that even
means that you can't even like lead them together. Okay. So let's
say you had them sort of, you know, yoked together and המנהיג
Ha-manhig and you were leading them and making them move together. סופג
את הארבעים. Sofeg et ha-arba'im. That would be considered כלאים Kilayim of
animals and you would get lashes.
והיושב בקרון, Ve-hayoshev ba-karon, but if you're sitting, let's say, in a
wagon and the two of them are yoked to the wagon and
they're pulling you,
so in that case, סופג את הארבעים, Sofeg et ha-arba'im, you also
get lashes. רבי מאיר פוטר ביושב בקרון. Rabbi Meir poter be-yoshev ba-karon.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no, the guy sitting in the wagon,
he's not really leading them, he's not really making them move, he
did not do the prohibition of, you know, חורש בשור וחמור. Choresh
be-shor ve-chamor. Okay. Now, ובהא איפכא שמואל. U-ve-ha ipcha Shmuel. Now שמואל
Shmuel actually reversed the names of that משנה. Mishna. ותני וחכמים פוטרים
את היושב בקרון. Ve-tani va-Chachamim potrim et ha-yoshev ba-karon. Said that the
חכמים Chachamim were the one who exempted the one sitting in the
wagon. So why did he reverse it? 'Cause obviously he liked the
position that the one sitting in the wagon was exempt and he
wanted that to be the majority position. So therefore he said it
was the חכמים Chachamim who taught that you're exempt. So now what
do you have? You have that here's a guy, now this is
really separate, this is not at the same time, but a guy
sitting in a wagon and he's saying it's not really meaningful. Okay.
שמע מינה רכוב לחודיה לא קני וכל שכן רכוב במקום מנהיג. Shema
mina rachuv lachudei lo kani ve-chol she-ken rachuv bimkom manhig. You see
from there that, you know, if שמואל Shmuel is פוסק-ing Posek that
you're not חייב Chayav because of שור וחמור יחדיו Shor ve-chamor yachdav
then by sitting in a wagon, so even by itself it's not
meaningful. So certainly it's not meaningful in competition with, you know, with
מנהיג. Manhig. All right. So it must be, you know, even though
you sort of remembered that it was a case or it seemed
to be a case of competing and which one was better, actually
from the evidence it seems that שמואל Shmuel held that רכוב Rachuv
is not קונה Koneh at all. Period. Now again, what exactly is
the relationship between whether it's the prohibition of, of, you know, of
leading an ox and a donkey together or whether it demonstrates ownership?
It's not at all clear how those are connected.
תוספות Tosafot says that we have to assume that the animal is
moving a little. because you're sitting on it, as opposed to the
מנהיג manhig that really is making it move, you know, a substantial
amount.
And therefore, because otherwise, you know, actually you have to ask yourself,
right, where did we ever get this idea of a קנין kinyan
of רכוב? rachuv? The קנין kinyan of animals is משיכה. meshicha. But
okay, so if it's moving a little, what we're thinking is, is
the guy who makes it move a lot קונה, koneh, you know,
is that stronger? Or the guy who makes it maybe take a
step or two, but because he's holding on, you know, to the
reins and whatever, that's a bigger משיכה meshicha than the guy who
makes it move a lot? So if that's the question, that they're
both a משיכה, meshicha, maybe one is qualitatively stronger, the other quantitatively,
then we can prove, oh look, here in this case of כלאים,
kilayim, just because it takes a step or two and you're sitting
on it, is not considered like you pulled them and you made
them move. So that would therefore demonstrate, if it's not considered like
you made them move for for כלאים, kilayim, you also it's not
like you made them move for משיכה. meshicha. That's how תוספות Tosfos
tries to connect the two. Otherwise it's just very strange, what does
the איסור issur of שור וחמור יחדיו shor vechamor yachdav have to
do with whether it demonstrates an act of a קנין? kinyan? All
right, but that's what we are right now, that it seems really
that שמואל Shmuel does not value רכוב rachuv at all.
אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף. Amar lei Abaye le-Rav Yosef. Now אביי
Abaye said to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, אביי Abaye was a student
of רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. הזימנין סגין אמרת לן במחזי עלן ולא
אמרת לן משמיה דרב יהודה. Zimnin sagin amrat lan bemachzei alan velo
amrat lan mishmei de-Rav Yehuda. So he says, you know רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, many times you sort of brought us this ראיה rayah
from this case, this evidence from this case of the of the
שור shor and the חמור, chamor, and it sounded like that was
your insight that that shows us that רכוב rachuv is not meaningful,
but based on the guy sitting in the in the wagon. You
never said that it was רב יהודה Rav Yehuda that made that
point. אמר ליה איברא, Amar lei ivra, yes it's true, you know,
you know, meaning I didn't say in the past it was רב
יהודה, Rav Yehuda, but it is רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, I now
remember that it was רב יהודה Rav Yehuda who used this to
prove that רכוב rachuv is not meaningful. ודחרינן נמי, Vedachrinan nami,
and I also remember that דאמר ליה de-amar lei היכי פשיט מר
רכוב מיושב? heichi pashit mar rachuv mi-yoshev?
That we challenged רב יהודה Rav Yehuda when רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
tried to bring this. And we said, how are you comparing the
case of sitting and be like, you know, and riding it, you
know, or being in a riding position from a case of just
sitting in a wagon? Right, besides that one is about the prohibition
of שור וחמור shor vechamor and one is about קנין, kinyan, but
just those two cases of sitting in a wagon is fundamentally different
than sitting on the saddle and holding on to the reins. רכוב
מיושב, יושב לא תפיס במוסירה. Rachuv mi-yoshev, yoshev lo tafis be-mosira.
The guy sitting in the wagon is not holding on to the
reins. רכוב תפיס במוסירה. Rachuv tafis be-mosira. And the guy sitting sitting
on the saddle is holding the reins. So even if the guy
in the wagon, what he's doing is not considered meaningful at all,
again, whether כלאים kilayim or קנין kinyan or whatever, the guy sitting
in the saddle holding onto the reins, that might actually be a
good קנין. kinyan. ואמר לי, Ve-amar li, so that's what I remember
I said, you know, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said,
עולא Ulla said רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said taught taught us this
and I pushed him back pushed back on him and said, you
know, what how can you compare the two? ואמר לי, Ve-amar li,
and then and then רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said to me, רב
ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו מוסירה לא קני. Rav u-Shmuel de-amri tarvaihu mosira lo
kani. No,
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both said that holding on to the
reins is not a קנין. kinyan. So it's clear to me, said
רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, that שמואל Shmuel does not treat רכוב rachuv
as a קנין. kinyan. Holding on to the reins by itself is
not meaningful as a קנין, kinyan, go back to that in a
second. Sitting in the wagon is not meaningful as a קנין, kinyan,
somehow we learn that out from כלאים. kilayim. So somehow just if
you take a zero and a zero and you put it together
you don't get something. Each one of those is not significant. Now
again, who knows, maybe not significant by itself, the combination of the
two, all not not clear, but that's what he said. All right.
Now, how is this true that holding on to the reins is
not a קנין? kinyan? Actually there's a classic קנין kinyan called מסירה,
mesira, handing over the reins. מוסירה Mosira is the reins or whatever,
מסירה. mesira. So we're going to see right now in the גמרא
Gemara that that's when somebody is transferring ownership. The handing over of
the reins can be a symbolic transfer of ownership. But the but
the holding the reins by itself does not show possession, control, ownership.
It's the act of handing them over. But the but the holding
on its own, by that works by a sale, by a מציאה,
metziah, the holding on its own is not significant.
So let's take a look. אמר ליה הכי תנא אידי... Amar lei
hachi tana idi... Wait a minute. רכוב תפיס במוסירה. Rachuv tafis be-mosira.
אמר ליה הכי תנא אידי. Amar lei hachi tana idi. This is
what אידי Idi taught: מוסירה לא קני. Mosira lo kani. And...
איתמר נמי, itmar nami, wait
I skipped a line, hold on, skip the line.
Okay,
so here we are. איכא דאמרי Ika de-amri others say, אמר ליה
אביי לרב יוסף, amar lei Abaye le-Rav Yosef, not that רב יוסף
Rav Yosef said this was the exchange I had with רב יהודה,
Rav Yehuda, but רב יהודה... Rav Yehuda... איכא דאמרי, ika de'amri, others
say, אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, amar leih Abbaye le-Rav Yosef, not
that רב יוסף Rav Yosef said this was the exchange I had
with רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, but אביי Abbaye said to רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, היכי פשיט מר רכוב מיושב, heichi pashit mar rachuv miyoshev,
this was when רב יוסף Rav Yosef presumably this was an earlier
version when רב יוסף Rav Yosef was teaching this idea of learning
it out from the wagon in his own name, not in the
name of רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, and he said we can see
from the case of the wagon
that רכוב rachuv is not a קנין. kinyan. And אביי Abbaye said
back to him, how can you apply the case of sitting in
a wagon of of being ridden of of like sitting in the
saddle and riding it from the case of sitting in a wagon?
יושב לא תפיס במוסירה רכוב תפיס במוסירה. yoshev lo tafis be-mosira, rachuv
tafis be-mosira. You know, again, the one in the wagon isn't holding
onto the reins, the one sitting in the saddle is holding onto
the reins. Exact same exchange except as opposed to it being an
exchange between עולא Ulla and רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, now the now
the version is that it was an exchange between אביי Abbaye and
עולא. Ulla. Okay, so again, but how can you bring a case
by the wagon that's not relevant to sitting in the saddle? אמר
ליה, amar leih,
and so maybe sitting in the saddle is stronger. And he said
back to him,
הכי תני אידי, hachi tani Idi, מוסירה לא קנה. mosira lo kana.
The holding the reins by a מציאה metzia is not a קנין.
kinyan. And since sitting is not a קנין kinyan and the reins
is not a קנין, kinyan, the combination of the two is also
not a קנין. kinyan. Not exactly clear how we know that, but
that's what we're saying. איתמר נמי itmar nami was also taught, אמר
רבי חלבו אמר רב הונא, amar Rabbi Chelbo amar Rav Huna, מסירה
מחבירו קנה. mesira mi-chaveiro kana. If somebody hands over the reins and
is doing a sale, it works. במציאה ובנכסי הגר לא קנה. be-metzia
u-ve-nichsei ha-ger lo kana. But if you if it's a lost object,
taking the reins, or if it's a גר ger who dies and
therefore nobody inherits and therefore it's basically free to be grabbed, taking
over the reins does not work. Okay, taking over the reins does
not show enough ownership, but the act of handing the reins shows
a transfer of ownership. מאי לשון מסירה? mai lashon mesira? What is
the meaning of the word מסירה, mesira, like reins? אמר רבא, amar
Rava, אידי אסברא לי. Idi asbra li. אידי Idi who is the
one who taught that other ברייתא beraita that the מסירה mesira by
itself doesn't work, explained it to me: כאדם המוסר דבר מחבירו לחבירו,
ke-adam ha-moser davar mi-chaveiro le-chaveiro,
like handing it over. So it's the act of handing which is
significant, it's not the holding of the reins. בשלמא מחבירו קנה. bishlama
mi-chaveiro kana.
So when you're buying it from somebody else you take possession, דקא
מסר ליה חבריה. de-ka masar leih chavrei. You have that act of
handing it over. אלא במציאה ובנכסי הגר מאן קא מסר ליה דלקני?
ela be-metzia u-ve-nichsei ha-ger man ka masar leih de-likni? Nobody is handing
it over. Okay, so what we see here is that that we
had this whole question of רכוב rachuv versus מנהיג, manhig, which one
is stronger, assuming that רכוב rachuv by itself worked. And then what
we wound up doing is we wound up saying that actually רכוב
rachuv by itself doesn't work. How? Somehow the fact that sitting in
a wagon is not meaningful by the איסור issur of שור וחמור
יחדיו, shor ve-chamor yachdav, that somehow tells us something that it's also
not meaningful for a קנין. kinyan. Again, not exactly clear how it
does that. And if that's not meaningful, the addition of sitting with
holding of the reins isn't meaningful because we know holding the reins
by itself is not meaningful. So therefore if each one by itself
isn't meaningful the combination isn't meaningful and therefore it's not even a
question of the competition between רוכב rochev and מנהיג. manhig. It's just
the issue of even רוכב rochev by itself does not actually work.
Okay, so מיתיבי meitivei says the גמרא Gemara one more piece, let
me ask you. השנים רוכבים על גבי בהמה, ha-shenayim rochvim al gabei
behema, two people were riding. מני? mani? Who's this going like? Now,
the presumption is that you can't this case of debating who picked
up the מציאה, metzia, who whatever, you have to be holding the
object in a way
that represents a type of a קנין kinyan that you would've that
would be a valid קנין kinyan on the object. Now, that's not
necessarily obvious, right? You could say what it means for me to
be in my possession to lay claim to it does not have
to be the same type of holding and the same type of
an act that I need to actually transfer ownership and take possession,
but that seems to be the assumption. So if these two people
are riding it, it seems like riding it is a קנין. kinyan.
How else could they lay claim to it and they each say
that they have rights to it? Okay,
מני? mani? Who's this going like? אילימא רבי מאיר, ilima Rabbi Meir,
if it's like רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? Again, the way we reversed
the ברייתא beraita that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir now we're having רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says that the guy sitting in the wagon, you
know, takes possession. So if that's true, I mean, excuse me, the
guy sitting in the wagon transgresses שור וחמור shor ve-chamor and therefore
presumably it would work as a קנין. kinyan. השתא יושב קנה רכוב
מבעיא? hashta yoshev kana rachuv miba'ya?
So why did he give a case of two people riding in
it? Why didn't he tell me a bigger חידוש? chiddush? Even if
two people were just sitting on it or like sitting in a
wagon.
You know, again, like to think that we want to say always
the biggest חידוש chiddush and it's a more natural scenario, two people
riding on it, but okay. If it was רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
who says that sitting in the wagon you're חייב chayav for שור
וחמור shor ve-chamor and therefore it works as a קנין, kinyan, it
should have told me here just two people sitting rather than two
people riding and holding the reins. אלא לאו רבנן? ela lav rabanan?
It must be the רבנן rabanan who say that sitting in the
wagon is not meaningful. ושמע מינה רכוב קנה. u-shema mina rachuv kana.
And it's showing you though that riding it, sitting there and holding
the reins, sitting in the saddle does work.
So גמרא *Gemara* says no. הכא במאי עסקינן במנהיג ברגליו *Hacha b'mai
askinan b'manhig b'raglav*.
When we talk about two people riding it, we don't mean that
they're just sitting there and holding the reins, it means they're actively
riding it, that the animal is they're kicking with their legs and
the animal is moving. So the type of thing that they're doing
here, even though they're seated in it, they're actually doing the קנין
*kinyan* of משיכה *meshicha*, the same type of a קנין *kinyan* that
a מנהיג *manhig* would be doing. אי הכי *Ei hachi* says the
גמרא *Gemara*, היינו מנהיג *hainu manhig*? So why does it talk about
two people riding or one people riding and one people being מנהיג
*manhig*? That's also just a variation of מנהיג *manhig*. So גמרא *Gemara*
says yeah, תרי גווני מנהיג *trei gavnei manhig*. Okay, there are two
types of מנהיג *manhig*. One is sitting and making it move and
the other is just pulling it. מהו דתימא *Mahu d'teima*, I might
have thought רכוב עדיף דמנהיג ותפיס ביה *rachuv adif d'manhig v'tafis bei*?
Maybe רכוב *rachuv* is stronger. This gets back to Shmuel's question. Now
this actually is a meaningful question. If you have one guy that's
רכוב *rachuv* and מנהיג *manhig* are both both work. If the רכוב
*rachuv* is something that kicks with his legs and makes it move,
those are two types of משיכה *meshicha*, each one works. And now
you can understand that Shmuel might have a question, if they're coming
together does one of them win out over the other? Okay, but
the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't go back to Shmuel's question, but it does
say that that's the scenario in our משנה *Mishna*. In our משנה
*Mishna* where it talks about רכוב *rachuv* working, that would be a
רכוב *rachuv* where you're kicking it and it's a type of a
משיכה *meshicha* and I might have thought that that's so much stronger
because you're sitting and making it move that it comes together with
מנהיג *manhig*, it beats out מנהיג *manhig*. Okay, רכוב עדיף דמנהיג ותפיס
ביה קא משמע לן *rachuv adif d'manhig v'tafis bei ka mashma lan*
that it doesn't, that they're equal. So basically what we've done is
we've said Shmuel had this whole question, but we've basically made it
moot. We've said רכוב *rachuv* by itself doesn't work, and a רכוב
*rachuv* that is making it move, that's a type of a מנהיג
*manhig*, a type of a משיכה *meshicha*, that does work and the
משנה *Mishna* is actually teaching that even though it works, it doesn't
beat out the מנהיג *manhig* and they're both equal and
therefore יחלוקו *yachaloku*.